Finding aid for the Xavier University Faculty Development Committee records
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections
Xavier University Faculty Development Committee records
1976-2013
1994-2013
Xavier University Archives and Special Collections Phone: 513-745-4821 http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Faculty Development Committee.
4 linear feet (10 boxes)
Correspondence, proposals, award notifications and other documents of the Xavier University Faculty Development Committee. Four financial awards are given: Faculty Development Leave, the Jesuit Faculty Fellowship Award, Summer Fellowships, and the Wheeler Award.
XUA- 5
History of the Faculty Development Committee Awards
The Xavier University Faculty Development Committee assists in the awarding of four financial awards: Faculty Development Leave, the Jesuit Faculty Fellowship Award, Summer Fellowships, and the Wheeler Award.
The Faculty Development Committee consists of five principal faculty representing all three colleges at Xavier University. The Faculty Development Committee reviews all applications and the Chair, together with the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs, submits the acceptable proposals to the Provost and CAO. The Committee indicates to the Provost and CAO its own judgment regarding priority among the proposals it submits. The Provost and CAO has the final voice in approving proposals for funding.
Faculty Development Committee members applying for a Faculty Development Award (e.g. Wheeler, Summer Fellowship. or Leave) must recuse themselves from all discussions pertaining to that award category. Faculty Development Leaves are available to Principal Faculty with a minimum of three years in the tenure-track position at Xavier. Tenure-track faculty may apply in the fall of their third tenure-track year. These grants may be at full salary for one semester or at one-half for two semesters. Recipients of faculty development leaves will generally be released from regular committee assignments for the period of the award. Within two months after the end of the leave or fellowship, the faculty member must submit a project report to the Ofice of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs and the faculty member's department chair and dean.
The endowed Faculty Fellowship competition is made possible by a generous gift from the Xavier Jesuit Community. The purpose of the Fellowship is to promote scholarship that enhances the service of faith and the promotion of justice. Each year, by means of a competition, a faculty member is selected as a Xavier Faculty Fellow. The Fellow is provided with a one semester leave with full salary, and a budget of $5,000 to cover expenses such as travel, student assistance, or materials related to the project. All full-time tenured or tenure track faculty from all disciplines are eligible to apply. Faculty Fellows are expected to present a seminar to the University Community within one academic year following the Fellowship.
Summer Fellowships are intended primarily, but not exclusively, for junior faculty members in the tenure-track position at Xavier. The current stipend is $4,000. the faculty member may teach one course or workshop during the summer of the award. Within two months after the end of the fellowship, the faculty member must submit a project report to the Office of the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs.
The Wheeler Academic Development Fund was established to support selected teaching activities related to improving academic programs. Monies for the fund were provided from the estate of Esther Wheeler, long-time administrative assistant in the Xavier Evening College. She was the wife of Professor Charles Wheeler, a former Chair of the English Department and the first Director of Summer Sessions. The Wheeler Awards are made to cover expenses associated with the following types of projects: 1, Individual Projects directed toward a faculty member developing new courses or new approaches to current courses, or 2, Group Projects directed toward improving or strengthening the capacities of programs and departments to meet their teaching responsibilities. The Wheeler Awards are to fund pilot programs and new initiatives and efforts, and not to replace existing sources of funding or to provide ongoing support for a program. (Source for the above information was the Xavier University Faculty Development web site, accessed September 10, 2013).
Scope and Content
Records resulting from the activities of the Xavier University Faculty Development Committee. Records include proposals, correspondence, award notifications, and other related documents.
Statement of Arrangement
The collection is divided into five series, as follows: Series I. General Information and Historical Materials Series II. Faculty Development Leave Materials Series III. Faculty Fellowship Award Materials Series IV. Summer Fellowship Materials Series V. Wheeler Award Materials
Restrictions on Access
Restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.
Acquisition Information
Materials (except those found in Series I: General Information and Historical Materials) were transferred to the Xavier University Archives from the Office of the Provost and Chief Academic Officer.
Accruals
There may be additional materials added to this collection at a later date.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Faculty; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Research Grants; Xavier University (Cincinnati,Ohio)--Awards
Organizations/Corporations:
Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Faculty Development Committee.; Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Office of the Provost and Chief Academic Officer.
- Series I: General Information, Correspondence and Historical Materials, 1976; 1988; 2007-2013
  - General Information and Historical Materials, 1976; 1988; 2007-2013 (Box 1)
- Series II: Faculty Development Leave, 1995-2013
  - Faculty Development Leave, 1995-2010 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Development Leave, 2010-2012 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Development Leave, 2012-2013 (Box 3)
- Series III: Faculty Fellowship Award, 2002-2013
  - Faculty Fellowship Award, 2002-2013 (Box 1)
- Series IV: Summer Fellowships, 2000-2012
  - Summer Fellowships, 2000-2008 (Box 1)
  - Summer Fellowships, 2009-2010 (Box 2)
  - Summer Fellowships, 2011-2012 (Box 3)
- Series V: Wheeler Award, 2001-2012
  - Wheeler Award, 2001-2010 (Box 1)
  - Wheeler Award, 2010-2012 (Box 2)